なんばむった
(南波六太)＜1993年１０月２８日
｢ドーハの悲劇｣＞
Japan is within reach of the World Cup!
Thursday, October 28th 1993
October 28th, 1993.
We're now approaching the ninety-minute mark.
The Agony of Doha.
Tortoise
Ladies Clinic
よせん
＜ワールドカップ最終予選で
日本は後ちょっとのところで➡
This should be the last play of the game.
In the World Cup preliminaries, Japan was seconds away from qualifying, when they gave up a goal...
A short corner.
He cuts right! Here's the last pass... A header!
ゴールを決められ…＞
[TV](ｱﾅｳﾝｻｰ)ヘディングシュート！
決められた～！
のが
＜本戦出場を逃してしまった＞
Goal!
And lost their chance.
＜どっかのおっさんの
ため息と同時に➡
It was a day of agony, as a certain old man groaned, while the entire nation sighed in exasperation.
だつりょく
日本中が脱力の深～いため息を
ひげき
吐きまくった｢悲劇の日｣＞
Again... Once again! Japan falls short at the very end!
ぼう
(赤ん坊)オギャア オギャア｡
(南波父)あっあ～っ出た！
He's out!
(赤ん坊)オギャア オギャア｡
ぼく
たんじょう
＜僕 誕生＞
And I was born.
[TV](ｱﾅｳﾝｻｰ)
ロッキーズ ゼロが８回まで｡
＜３年後の1996年９月１７日＞
The Rockies remain scoreless through eight innings.
Tuesday, September 17th 1996
Eight zeros on the board. No hits.
Three years later, September 17th, 1996.
Hare
Ladies Clinic
のも
＜野茂がメジャーでノーヒット
たっせい
ノーランを達成した…＞
Nomo pitched a no-hitter.
Come on, Nomo!
[TV](ｱﾅｳﾝｻｰ)
さあ 野茂 ノーヒットノーラン
に向けて あとアウト一つ！
Only one more out for the no-hitter shutout!
えいこう
＜栄光の日＞
からぶさんしん
[TV](ｱﾅｳﾝｻｰ)空振り三振！➡
A day of glory.
Three strikes!
ノーヒットノーラン！
A complete shutout!
かんせい
＜日本中で大歓声が
わくと同時に…＞
While the entire nation erupted in cheers,
[TV](ｱﾅｳﾝｻｰ)
いだいきろく
偉大な記録をうちたてました！
He's left his mark on history!
(赤ん坊)オギャア オギャア｡
＜弟 誕生＞
my brother was born.
＜そして2006年７月９日＞
And on July 9th, 2006...
Sunday, July 9th 2006
＜この日 行われたドイツ
ワールドカップ決勝戦で➡
During the 2006 German World Cup final,
ずつき
さくれつ
ジダンの頭突きが炸裂！＞
Zidane headbutted an opposing player.
Oh, now...
たいじょう
[TV](ｱﾅｳﾝｻｰ)あ～！ジダン退場！➡
Oh, Zidane's been ejected!
げんえき
ジダンの現役最後の
ゲームは退場～！
He's been ejected from the final game of his career!
While the rest of the world was shocked by Zidane's outburst,
＜世界中がジダンに
どぎも
度肝を抜かれていた頃➡
僕達兄弟は…＞
we brothers were...
俺は前回より先を調査する！
I'm going to explore farther out than last time.
りょうかい
(南波日々人)了解｡
Roger.
つね
＜兄とは常に弟の先を
行ってなければならない＞
A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother.
つと
＜それが兄としての務め＞
That is his duty for having been born earlier.
Space Brothers
Ah
This feels so good, different from usual
I have no idea what's going on
It feels so good
I never understand what's going on around me
Nothing makes sense to me
Full of questions
Feel so moon
I danced with you in a desert lit by the moon
I won't lose to the rabbit and fly high
I'll fly high
#01 Little Brother Hibito and Big Brother Mutta
フフッフフッ お？
あれ？どっち行くんだっけ？
Huh?
Which way should I go?
ヘッヘヘヘ｡
July 9th, 10:01 PM.
７月９日２２時１分｡
うらしげ
竹の子ニュータウン裏の茂みにて
ニホンアマガエル…｡
Discovered a Japanese tree frog in the thicket behind Bamboo Newtown.
ヘッヘヘッヘヘヘ｡
いて…｡
Ow.
Oh, found ya!
あっ見～っけ！
つぎ
２２時０３分 次田川中流｡
10:03 PM, Tsugida, mid-stream.
ムッちゃぁ～ん!!
Mu!
ムッちゃん こっち来いよ！早く！
Mu, over here! Quick!
What?
早く来いってば！ムッちゃん！
Hurry up, Mu!
な～に～？
遅いよ！もう！
What is it?
You're so slow...
Whoa!
こ こら！日々人！こら！
Hey, Hibi... Hibito!
Stop this!
はなして～！
P-Put me down...
ぶへっ！
おろして｡
Put me down.
日々人 お前な～！あ？
Hibito! Come on...
Huh?
うっうっ 何あれ!?
What's that?
わかんない…｡
No idea.
うわあ！なんだよ｡
Oh... What's it doing?
ハアッ｡
つ 月…行った？
I-It went to the moon?
Year 2025
来年の春 我々は月へ旅立ちます｡
Next spring, we will be heading to the moon.
ぞんじ
ご存知の通り 我々が月で
たいざい
長期滞在するための➡
As you already know, supplies have been transported to the moon,
うんぱん
物資の運搬は
すでに終えています｡➡
to sustain an extended stay.
我々のミッションは
言ってみれば➡
In essence, this mission
火星移住のための
リハーサルのようなものです｡➡
is a rehearsal for the colonization of Mars.
ぶたい
きょじゅう
こうちく
月を舞台に居住環境を構築し
じっせん
長期滞在を実践します｡
We will construct a viable ecosystem, and attempt long-term habitation.
なるほど 今回のミッションの
目的がよくわかりました｡➡
Fascinating.
You certainly have clarified this mission's objective.
でも実はＵＦＯを
探しに行くんじゃないか➡
But some rumors claim that you're searching for UFOs.
という説もあるようですが…｡
今回 初フライトのお一人が
その辺 お詳しいですよね？
I believe that your newest crew member can shed some light on the matter?
ああ もしかして僕のことですか？
Oh, you mean me?
コホン！え～ご心配なく｡
Yes, please don't worry.
にんむ
月では任務に集中しますので｡
When we reach the moon, the mission will be my focus.
すいません マイク持たないで｡
Excuse me, could you let go of the mic?
Oh...
In a recent interview,
しゅつえん
たしかに先日テレビに出演中
｢ＵＦＯを見たことがある｣➡
I did mention that I once saw a UFO,
と言ってしまいましたが
それは子供の頃の話です｡
but that was when I was a kid.
あれが本当にＵＦＯだったか
どうかは わかりませんが➡
I have no idea whether it really was a UFO,
今 僕が ここにいるキッカケに
なったことは たしかです｡
but I can say that it is the reason I'm here.
(男性記者)では南波日々人さん➡
So, Nanba Hibito,
げつめんちゃくりく
日本人初の月面着陸者になる
ことをどう思われますか？
how does becoming the first Japanese person to set foot on the moon feel?
日本人にとって
月は昔から特別な存在です｡
The moon has always held special meaning for the Japanese.
そこへ国を代表して行けることは
とても光栄です｡ですが…｡
I am honored to serve as my country's ambassador to the moon.
However...
僕より先に月面を
踏むはずだった人が➡
There was someone who was supposed to step upon the moon before me,
今 この場にいないのは
残念です｡
and it's unfortunate that he couldn't be here right now.
(運転手)お荷物は以上ですね｡
(後輩)ああ はい｡
Is that everything?
Oh, yes.
では南波さん お乗り下さい｡
(後輩)いや 僕じゃないです｡
Please get in, Nanba.
Oh, no, I'm not Nanba.
南波は俺です｡
I'm Nanba!
うわっと～！
Nanba...
南波先輩！
大丈夫っすか？
Are you okay?
ひにく
ふっ…皮肉なもんだ｡
Heh, the irony.
自分で設計して賞まで取った車で
見送られるなんてな｡
They're sending me off in the award-winning car I designed.
Nanba, I don't know what to say.
南波先輩…なんと言ったら
いいか｡僕たち…｡
We're...
気にするな！リストラなんて
よくある悲劇さ｡
Don't worry about it.
People lose their jobs every day.
悲劇には慣れてる！｢ドーハの
しゅくめい
悲劇生まれ｣の宿命だよ｡
I'm used to suffering.
That's what happens when you're born during the Agony of Doha.
(運転手)どうぞ｡
(３人)《また言ってる…》
Please get in.
There he goes again.
最後に一つ 君たちに
大事なことを言っておく｡
I have one last word of advice for you kids...
間違っても俺のように上司に
頭突きなんかしちゃダメだよっ｡
Do not, under any circumstances,
headbutt your supervisor like I did!
(運転手)出発しま～す｡
じゃあねえぇ！
We're leaving now.
Bye!
＜2025年５月１５日
わたくし南波六太は➡
May 15th, 2025.
I, Nanba Mutta, lost my job with an automobile manufacturer.
晴れて自動車開発会社を退職＞
＜我が弟のことを悪く
言いやがった上司に私は➡
After my supervisor insulted my brother,
やってしまった＞
Zidane!
I couldn't help myself.
＜もちろん一発退場＞
Naturally, I was fired immediately.
After losing my job, I was forced to move back in with my parents.
＜社宅を追放され
きょうせいそうかん
実家へ強制送還だ＞
(運転手)では お気をつけて｡
Please take care then.
どうすんだ？この荷物｡
What am I supposed to do with all these boxes?
無職かぁ…アハハ｡
Unemployed...
無職！ハハハ！
Unemployed!
ハハハ！ア～ッハハハ｡
帰ったら泣こう…｡
I'll cry when I get home.
Three Weeks Later
(南波母)六太～ごはん～！
六太～！
Mutta, dinner's ready!
Mutta!
(母)六太！ごはん！
Mutta, time for dinner!
グア…あ…今いく｡
Yeah, I'm coming...
＜私が帰ってきた時の
大歓迎ムードは とうに薄れ➡
It's safe to say that I've worn out my warm welcome.
(母)((オーケーイ ハハハ！))
＜大はしゃぎだった母も
もはや このテンション＞
Welcome home!
At first, my mother was excited, but that didn't last long.
もく
＜父は黙して語らず＞
My father hasn't said a word.
TV Drama
Son of Mine
[TV]もう お前は息子じゃない！
出てけっ！
[TV]父さん!!
You're no son of mine...
Get out!
Dad...
＜そして私は 気づいていた＞
And I noticed something else.
＜デザートのイチゴに至っては
私のだけ２個少ない＞
When it came time for dessert,
she gave me two fewer strawberries.
はぁ…わかったよ｡
I get the message...
明日から ちゃんと仕事探すよ｡
だから イチゴとかさ…｡
I'll start looking for a job tomorrow,
so about those strawberries...
(母･父)はい｡
Here.
[TV]父さん 母さん
僕は必ず大きくなって戻るぞ｡➡
Mom, Dad, I'll grow big and return!
あっ！すべった！わ～っ!!
Ah, I tripped...
いってきます｡
I'm off!
Vacation's over...
《お休みは 終わりだ｡➡
今日から 新しい俺
ニュームッタの始まりだ！》
I'm starting over. You'll see a new Mutta!
Automobile Company
南波六太さん…
大学では機械工学を専攻されて➡
Nanba Mutta.
You majored in mechanical engineering.
ミラクルカー社さんで ほう！
ﾅﾝﾊﾞｰｼｯｸｽの設計主任をされた!?
はい！
You worked at Miracle Car.
Oh...
You designed the No. 6!
I did.
あの車は確か 去年の
ｸﾞｯﾄﾞｲｶｽｶｰ賞をとってますよね｡
いやあ ハイ｡
I believe that car won last year's Good Snazzy Car award.
Ah, yes...
でも どうして頭突きなどを？
But why would you headbutt your supervisor?
Huh?
グッ グッ グッ…プハーッ！
おじちゃん どいて～｡
は～い｡
Move, old guy.
Sure.
＜私が頭突きをした
お偉いさんの計らいで➡
The boss I headbutted had spread the word,
他社の他社まで
私の悪評は広まっていた＞
so I was blacklisted at all the other companies.
＜私は二度と 自動車開発業界には
戻れそうにない＞
I doubt I'll ever work for an auto company again.
Man...
《あ～あ…なんだかもう
どうでもよくなってきた…》
I'm starting to have a hard time caring.
((ムッちゃん 俺 今…))
Mu, I...
日々人…
お前は夢を叶えたんだな｡
Hibito,
you've fulfilled your dream...
＜兄とは 常に弟の先を
行ってなければならない＞
A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother.
＜だけど…何をやっても
俺を追い越し 先を行くのは➡
But somehow,
my little brother, Hibito, always ends up ahead of me!
弟 日々人じゃないか！＞
《俺は…ん？》
What...
What have I been doing with my life?
《俺は今まで…
何がやりたかったんだろうか》
えっ!?それ どういうこと？
ムッちゃん そっちに帰ってんの？
Huh?
What do you mean?
Mu's home?
That's right!
そうなの！役員さんに頭突きして
クビになったの あの子｡
He headbutted his superior and got himself fired.
面白いでしょう｡
[ｲｱﾎﾝ]頭突き!?どうして？
Isn't that hilarious?
Headbutted? Why?
さあねえ｡あの子 そういう事
聞いても言わないでしょ｡だから➡
Beats me...
He never talks to us about that stuff.
That's why...
あっ！これ内緒の話だったんだ｡
Oh, I was supposed to keep it secret.
[ｲｱﾎﾝ](母)日々人には言うなって
口止めされてたの｡➡
He told me not to tell you...
あたし うっかりだわ～！
Oops, I forgot!
そうか…｡じゃあ今
ムッちゃんは？
[ｲｱﾎﾝ](母)就職活動！
Really...
Then, what's Mu doing now?
Job hunting.
仕事探しをしてんだな？
[ｲｱﾎﾝ](母)そうなのよ｡
応援してやって｡
He's looking for work?
That's right! Cheer up!
母さん…ムッちゃんのためにさ
ちょっと手伝ってくれよ｡
Mom...
I need you to help me with something. For Mu.
た～いま…｡
I'm home.
(母)おけ～りぃ｡
Welcome home!
Mohri...
《毛利さん…》
《あの時…》
At that moment...
＜あの時 毛利さんは 私達の背に
手を添えてくれていた＞
At that moment, when Mohri placed his hands our backs...
＜まるで力をくれるように＞
As if he were giving us a push...
＜私達兄弟は その時
同じ事を思ったに違いない＞
At that moment, we brothers had the same thought.
＜この人が見てきた宇宙へ
自分も行くんだと＞
We would go into space, the way he had.
毛利さん 日々人がやりましたよ｡
あいつは月へ行きます｡
Mohri, Hibito actually did it.
He's going to the moon.
《ちなみに僕は…もうダメです》
But I'm all washed up...
《ごきげんよう》
Good night.
はい 南波でございます｡
あれ？
Hello? This is Nanba.
Huh?
あ メールか｡
日々人？
An e-mail?
Hibito?
Where I did put it?
どこ置いたっけ？
全然違った…｡
This isn't it.
Hibito
Mu, are you okay?
Mom told me that you lost your job.
Hibito
If you haven't found a new job yet,
you should listen to the tape
you recorded on the 9th of July, 2006.
あ～ これか？
…これだ｡
Oh, is this it?
It is.
2006...
２００６年…｡
７月９日｡
July 9th.
I'd never really listened to the tape I recorded that day.
＜あの日
録音していた このテープ➡
私は 特に聴くことはなかったが➡
日々人は 自分で録音していた
あの日のカセットテープだけは➡
But Hibito really treasured
お守りのように
大事に持っていたという＞
the ones he'd recorded.
Treasure       Chest
《何で 今頃このテープを？》
Why would he want me to listen to it now?
おおっ！…ふぅ…｡
Discovered a Japanese tree frog in the thicket behind Bamboo Newtown.
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]裏の茂みにて
ニホンアマガエル…｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ](ゲコゲコゲコ…)
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]ムッちゃ～ん！ムッちゃん
こっち来いよ！早く!!
Mu!
Mu, over here! Quick!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]なぁに～？
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]遅いよ もう!!
What is it?
You're so slow...
Whoa!
Hey, Hibi...
Hibito! Stop this!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]何？あれ…｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]わかんない！
What's that?
No idea.
This is when the UFO showed up.
《ここでＵＦＯが…》
な 何だ？ このノイズ!?
Wh-Why is there static?
《こんな音 あの時は…！》
I don't remember any static.
《おお…マジかよ!?》
Oh...
Seriously?
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]月…行った？
I-It went to the moon?
Mu, I really think...
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]ムッちゃん 俺 今なんとなく➡
I really think I want to become an astronaut.
なんとなく
将来は宇宙飛行士になってさ➡
月に行くような気がしたよ｡
I believe I can make it to the moon.
H-He beat me to it!
《先に言われた！》
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]ムッちゃんは どうすんだ？
What about you, Mu?
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]え？俺？お 俺は…➡
Huh? Me?
I-I...
I...
俺は…｡
《俺は 何て言った？》
What did I say?
If you're going to the moon,
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]お前が月に行くんなら➡
兄ちゃんは
その先に行くに決まってる｡
then I'll stay one step ahead.
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]俺は…➡
I'm...
火星に行くよ！
going to Mars.
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]じゃあ 約束な｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]おお 約束だ｡
Then it's a promise.
Y-Yeah... A promise.
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]俺らは２人で
宇宙飛行士になるぞ｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]うん｡
We two will become astronauts.
Yep.
約束…｡
A promise...
日々人が俺に聞かせたかったのは
ここか…｡
That was what Hibito wanted me to hear.
Are you telling me to keep my promise,
《俺に この約束を
果たせって言ってるのか？》
《日々人…》
Hibito?
One Month Later
い １万だと？ふざけるな!!
T-Ten thousand?!
That's absurd!
ちょっと弁当買ってた
１０分かそこらだろ！
I was only gone ten minutes to buy some lunch!
それで罰金１万って
どういう計算してんだよ！
How does that warrant a ten-thousand yen fine?
黙ってね～で何とか言ってみろ！
お前 モジャモジャ！
Don't just stand there!
Say something, shaggy!
Uh, actually, it's fifteen thousand yen.
いや あの…１万５千円です｡
うるさい!!黙れ！
１万だろうが１万５千だろうが➡
Quiet! Shut up!
I won't pay ten thousand or fifteen thousand!
そんな金を払ういわれは
ないんだよ！
Look at all the spaces!
大体 こんな広い道路なんだ…｡
《ふふっ 皮肉なもんだぜ➡
I'm hardly blocking traffic, by parking here for a minute!
Heh, the irony.
この違反車も俺の設計｡
かわいそうにな…》
I designed this car, too.
That shaggy haired guy probably blocks more traffic than I do!
Poor thing...
聞いてるのか モジャモジャ！
何とか言ってみろ!!
Are you listening to me, shaggy?
Got anything to say for yourself?
い １万５千円です…｡
うるさい！黙れ 黙れ!!➡
I-It's fifteen thousand yen.
Quiet! Shut up! Shut up!
Your numbers can't be right!
大体 どういう計算で…｡
《あ～あ また別の仕事探すか…➡
Man, I should look for a different job...
Do you know how many lunches 15,000 yen buys?
早く帰って
読みかけの本を読みたい｡➡
I want to go home and finish reading my book.
And though it wasn't meant to be...
叶わぬ夢とはわかってるけど…➡
あ～あ｡また昔のように
宇宙の妄想に浸りたい…》
Man...
I want to go back to dreaming about space.
《結局 また仕事辞めてしまった》
I ended up quitting another job.
≪早く来いよ！早く早く！≫
Hurry up! Hurry up!
≪待ってよ お兄ちゃ～ん！≫
Wait up, bro...
早く来いよ！
お兄ちゃ～ん！
Hurry up!
Bro!
A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother,
《兄とは 常に弟の先を
行ってなければならない｡➡
だが俺は…次への一歩を
踏み出せてもいないじゃないか》
but I can't even take the next step!
《日々人 悪いが
あの約束は忘れてくれ…》
Hibito...
Sorry, but could you just forget that promise?
た～いまっ…｡
I'm home...
(母)おけ～りっ！
Welcome home.
Tokyo Metropolitan Area
High-West, Low-East City
Bamboo Newtown
Mr. Nanba Mutta
俺に？
To me?
JAXA?
ＪＡＸＡ？
Why would JAXA send me anything?
何でＪＡＸＡが 俺宛てに？
The New Astronaut Selection
Examination
新規宇宙飛行士選抜試験？
The New Astronaut Selection Exam?
Huh?
Your application has been accepted.
書類選考を通過？
Your application has been accepted...
Your application has been accepted.
私が出したのよ｡
あんたの履歴書｡
I sent them your résumé.
＜私は この時…➡
I don't remember
what expression I had on my face.
どんな顔をしていたのか
はっきりとは覚えていない｡➡
だがおそらく
最大限にしわくちゃな感じで➡
But it was probably all scrunched up,
泣いていたような
笑っていたような＞
as I wept and smiled...
おい 六太 帰ってんなら
あかりぐらいつけろ｡
Hey, Mutta.
If you're home, you should turn on the lights.
じゃあ 日々人 訓練を始めよう｡
ＯＫ！
Okay, Hibito...
We'll commence training.
Okay.
《早く来いよ ムッちゃん！》
Come soon, Mu.
The stars I admired were too bright for me
so I quietly closed my eyes
I have faith in you, as you stand alone, full of doubts
I'm right here, next to you
Come now, take my hand and hold it tight
If you do, we will always
have hope, shine with light
and overcome whatever we might face
Do you see how wonderful this world is
and how our future unfolds?
Even the tears we shed and could not put into words
will one day dry up, I am sure
One by one the smiles spread
and ascend towards the starlit sky
＜書類選考 通ったの
1225人中 315人だって＞
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#02 My Shining Star
Out of 1,225 applicants, 315 were accepted.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)＜凄いじゃない｡
それに通るなんて｡➡
Then you did well to pass.
六太の実力なら通るって
わかってたのね 日々人は…＞
Hibito must have known you were qualified.
＜無理だよ｡宇宙飛行士になれるの
なんて ２人か３人だよ＞
It's impossible!
Only two or three can become astronauts!
＜日々人の気持ちは
正直 スゲ～嬉しかったけど…＞
I was happy to know how Hibito felt.
Next time, on Space Brothers:
My Shining Star.
＜このまま行くと 兄貴の俺が
引っ張られることになる＞
At this rate,
the little brother will lead the older one.
This Week's Space Photo
パンパカパ－ン！
まもなく宇宙に行く
星出宇宙飛行士が➡
Every week, we'll present photographs
毎週送ってくれる
写真を紹介しま～す｡
すっげえ！
of astronauts heading out to space.
Awesome!
名付けて｢今週の宇宙写真｣｡
楽しみ！
Also known as "This Week's Space Photo!"
I can't wait!